{"tossups": [{"question": "One man with this surname published an abolitionist newspaper titled True American. That politician was the cousin of another man of this surname who, in 1816, was made president of the American Colonization Society. That man with this surname served three terms as Speaker of the House, including one in which he made a \u201ccorrupt bargain\u201d with John Quincy Adams to sway the election of 1824. For ten points, give the surname of the prominent Kentucky politicians Cassius and Henry.", "answer": "<em><b> Clay</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "At this battle, a sudden rainstorm rendered many of the crossbows of Carlo Grimaldi\u2019s contingent unusable. One commander in this battle refused to come to the aid of the Black Prince, saying \u201clet the boy win his spurs\u201d as he resisted an attack in which John the Blind was killed. This defeat for Philip VI led to the capture of Calais. For ten points, name this 1346 battle in which the English longbow was used to great effect against the French.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Crecy</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This leader first rose to prominence as mayor of Davao City. After UN criticism of extrajudicial killings by this leader, he responded by threatening to withdraw his nation from the UN. In September, 2016, this leader expressed a desire to kill as many people as Hitler did in the Holocaust. After his election, this leader launched an all out war on drugs, encouraging the population to kill drug addicts and drug dealers. For ten points, name this President of the Philippines.", "answer": "Rodrigo \u201cRody\u201d<em><b> Duterte</b></em> (prompt on \u201cDigong\u201d)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "As a colony, this modern-day state passed the Halifax Resolves, the first document advocating for independence from Britain. The building of the opulent Tryon Palace in this state\u2019s city of New Bern sparked the War of the Regulation. Despite heavy losses, Charles Cornwallis led the British to victory over Nathaniel Greene\u2019s forces at a battle in this state. For the point, name this state where the Battle of Guilford Courthouse took place in Greensboro.", "answer": "<em><b> North Carolina</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A 1930 opera based on a man born in this city had a libretto written by Paul Claudel. That Verdi opera is named for the first doge of this city, Simon Boccanegra. A Darius Milhaud [mee-yohd] opera focusing on a man born in this city uses Spanish themes to symbolize the title character\u2019s departure from Cadiz. For ten points, name this Italian city, the birthplace of the subject of the opera Christophe Colomb.", "answer": "<em><b> Genoa</b></em> (accept<em><b> Genova</b></em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "An Aksumite invasion of this city supposedly failed when the lead war elephant refused to enter it. A group of militants led by Juhayman al-Otaybi laid siege to a building in this city in 1979. This city was briefly the capital of the Kingdom of Hejaz after the dissolution of the Ottoman Empire. The Quraysh tribe of this city was defeated in the Battle of the Trench. For ten points, name this city at which the annual \u201cstoning of the devil\u201d ceremony occurs at the Kaaba.", "answer": "<em><b> Mecca</b></em>, Saudi Arabia", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "After his most celebrated invention, this man engaged in a debate over whether a \u201cmicro\u201d or\u201cmonolithic\u201d version of a program was superior. That debate was between this man and Andrew Tanenbaum. After coming under fire for using BitKeeper this man developed a free version called Git. Red Hat offers a business version of an operating system based around this man\u2019s kernel. For ten points, name this developer and namesake of the open-source operating system Linux.", "answer": "Linus Benedict<em><b> Torvalds</b></em>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Computer Science"}, {"question": "The ratified version of this agreement included protections for land on which both Peter Hargous and A.G. Sloo planned to build a railroad. That railroad secured in this agreement was never built but had been intended to cross the Isthmus of Tehauntepec. Ownership of the Mesilla Valley was resolved in this agreement which had been left undecided at the earlier negotiations to end the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this American land acquisition agreement with Mexico.", "answer": "<em><b> Gadsden Purchase</b></em> (accept<em><b> Gadsden Treaty</b></em>, accept<em><b> Treaty</b></em> of<em><b> Mesilla</b></em> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1797 a hypnotist from Goa was sent to a prison off the coast of this city where wealthy inhabitants could afford rooms called pistoles which were larger than typical cells. A fort built during the reign of Francis I served as the site of this city\u2019s basilica Notre-Dame de la Garde. Abbe Faria and Edmond Dantes were imprisoned in the Chateau d\u2019If [DEEF] off this city in The Count of Monte Cristo. For ten points, name this city in the south of France in what was once the ancient Greek colony of Massalia.", "answer": "<em><b> Marseille</b></em>, France", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "This politician controversially used the phrase \u201ccoffee-house babble\u201d to describe a report of foreign atrocities, but he regardless sent Lord Salisbury to negotiate at the Constantinople Conference. This man, who led the Young England movement after breaking with Robert Peel, signed the Royal Titles Act, conferring the title of \u201cEmpress of India\u201d upon Queen Victoria who favored this man more than his liberal rival. For ten points, name this 19th century British prime minister, the rival of William Gladstone.", "answer": "Benjamin<em><b> Disraeli</b></em>, 1st Earl of Beaconsfield (accept Earl of<em><b> Beaconsfield</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This Native American tribe adopted many colonial children, including Eunice Williams, following the Raid on Deerfield during Queen Anne\u2019s War. One leader of these people led a namesake group of Loyalists during the American Revolution known as \u201cBrant\u2019s Volunteers.\u201d Known as the \u201cKeepers of the Eastern Door,\u201d these people are the easternmost member of the Iroquois Confederacy. For ten points, name this tribe for whom a central New York river and valley are named.", "answer": "<em><b> Mohawk</b></em> (accept<em><b> Kanien\u2019keha:ka</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The final battle of this period, Wavre, failed to affect its outcome as it prevented the troops of Emmanuel de Grouchy from being deployed elsewhere. Though Gebhard von Blucher was shot off his horse at this period\u2019s battle of Ligny, he returned to aid the British during an engagement in a Belgian town. For ten points, identify this period in which Napoleon\u2019s return to power culminated in a defeat at Waterloo, named for its approximate length in the spring and summer of 1815.", "answer": "<em><b> Hundred Days</b></em> War (accept<em><b> War</b></em> of the<em><b> Seventh Coalition</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This author won a posthumous Tony Award for Lucky Guy, her story of the police brutality-exposing reporter, Mike McAlary. The first of this author\u2019s three Oscar nominations was for a 1983 biopic about labor activist and whistleblower Karen Silkwood. This writer\u2019s final screenplay was the first major film adaptation of a blog, fictionalizing Julie Powell\u2019s experiences with cooking. For ten points, name this American filmmaker who wrote Sleepless in Seattle and Julie & Julia.", "answer": "Nora<em><b> Ephron</b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "While a member of SASO, this man presented a paper on \u201cWhite Racism and Black Consciousness.\u201dFearing that he would be monitored by police, Unity Movement leader Neville Alexander refused to meet with this man. Five police officers confessed before the Truth and Reconciliation Commission to having tortured this man who coined the phrase \u201cBlack is beautiful\u201d in a Pretoria prison. For ten points, name this founder of the Black Consciousness Movement and anti-Apartheid activist.", "answer": "Steve<em><b> Biko</b></em> (accept Bantu Stephen<em><b> Biko</b></em>, prompt on \u201cFrank Talk\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This writer argued against the Brown v. Board decision in \u201cCourt Order Can\u2019t Make the Races Mix.\u201dThis writer described living in Eatonville, Florida and studying under Franz Boas in the autobiography Dust Tracks on a Road. Alice Walker revived interest in this writer when she claimed to have found her unmarked grave and wrote an article titled \u201cIn Search of,\u201d this writer. For ten points, name this anthropologist, folklorist, and novelist who also wrote Their Eyes Were Watching God.", "answer": "Zora Neale<em><b> Hurston</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s attempt to set up the New Virginia Colony and the Carlota Colony failed. Conservatives hated this man for abolishing child labor, and liberals hated this man for having been installed by foreign powers. This man refused to abandon his followers despite Napoleon III withdrawing his forces but was eventually defeated by Benito Juarez\u2019s forces and executed. For ten points, who was this second and last Emperor of Mexico?", "answer": "<em><b> Maximilian I</b></em>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This politician was one of the plaintiffs in the landmark 1976 campaign finance case Buckley v. Valeo. An informal slogan from this man\u2019s hippie supporters suggested they would \u201cGet clean.\u201d This politician\u2019s unexpectedly strong finish in the New Hampshire primary was one factor in Lyndon Johnson\u2019s withdrawal from that race. For ten points, name this Minnesota senator who unsuccessfully ran on an anti-war platform for the 1968 Democratic presidential nomination.", "answer": "<em><b> Eugene McCarthy</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In one phase of this battle, 200 sailors were killed when a bomb pierced the armor of the USS Princeton. The USS Darter successfully sunk the Atago during an engagement at (+) Palawan Passage during this battle. A radio silence that prevented Shoji Nishimura from communicating with other admirals allowed Jesse Oldendorf to set a trap during the Battle of (*) </b> Surigao Strait within this larger battle. This battle marked the first use of kamikaze attacks by Japan. For ten points, name this World War Two battle, possibly the largest naval engagement in history.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Leyte Gulf</b></em>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Prior to this campaign, German forces were deployed at Hitler\u2019s orders in \u201cFeste Platze,\u201d[PLET-zeh] fortified towns that were to be held at any cost. The largest single German defeat of the war occurred during this campaign when much of Army Group Centre was surrounded in the (+) Minsk Pocket. This operation ended after the securing of bridgeheads on the Vistula, as the victors controversially failed to aid the (*) </b> Warsaw Uprising. For ten points, name this 1944 Soviet operation that recaptured Belarus during World War Two, codenamed for a Russian commander of the Napoleonic Wars.", "answer": "Operation<em><b> Bagration</b></em> [buh-gruh-tee-ON] (accept<em><b> Belorussian</b></em> <em><b>Strategic</b></em> <em><b>Offensive</b></em> Operation before \u201ccodenamed\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Lipona Plantation, just east of this city, was the residence of Prince Achille Murat, a nephew of Napoleon. The Columns, built in 1830, is this city\u2019s oldest building and stands next to the (+) Leon County Library. This city is the site of an historic reproduction of the Franciscan mission, San Luis de Apalachee. A state university in this city plays football at (*)</b> Doak Campbell Stadium and was founded in 1851 as a compromise location between Pensacola and Saint Augustine. For ten points, name this city, the largest city in the \u201cBig Bend\u201d and the \u201cPanhandle\u201dof Florida.", "answer": "<em><b> Tallahassee</b></em>, Florida", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>This man combined his Confucian and Catholic beliefs to develop a system of government known as Personalism. Cable 243 indicated that foreign forces would not oppose a coup against this man after he had sent secret police to attack the (+) Xa Loi [SAH LOY] Pagoda. During this man\u2019s tenure, he ordered liquid chemicals to be poured on protestors at Hue [HWA]. The monk (*) </b> Thich Quang Duc [TIK KWONG DUK] set himself on fire to protest this man\u2019s rule. For ten points, name this leader of South Vietnam in the early stages of the Vietnam War.", "answer": "<em><b> Ngo</b></em> Dinh Diem", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This art form takes its name from the Japanese for \u201cfloating world,\u201d a description of the hedonistic lifestyle enjoyed by the 17th century Edo merchant class. Van Gogh copied one of these artworks, (+) Sudden Shower over Atake, during a phase he described as Japonaiserie. This art form declined under the (*)</b> technological modernization of the Meiji Restoration. For ten points, name this art form, practiced by Hiroshige and Hokusai and notably used for The Great Wave off Kanagawa, a Japanese form of woodblock printing.", "answer": "<em><b> Ukiyo-e</b></em> [oo-KEE-oh eh] (prompt on \u201cJapanese woodblock prints\u201d and similar or partial answers)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>One ruler of this name issued the mining code Ius regale montanorum after silver was discovered at Kutna Hora. Drahomira arranged to have Saint (+) Ludmila, the grandmother of another ruler of this name, killed at Tetin Castle. That ruler with this name was murdered by his younger brother Boleslav at the feast of Saints Cosmas and Damian. A ruler of the Premyslid [PREM-iss-lid] dynasty with this name is buried in Saint Vitus Cathedral in (*) </b>Prague. For ten points, give this name of four kings of Bohemia, the first of whom is commemorated in a song for giving alms on the Feast of Stephen.", "answer": "<em><b> Wenceslas</b></em> (accept<em><b> Vaclav</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>In this author\u2019s autobiography, he described suffering shrapnel wounds to the lung during the Battle of Somme while a member of the Royal Welsh Fusiliers. In a novel by this author, the title character is advised to love history by his tutor, Athenodorus, and to survive by acting foolish by his idol, (+) Asinius Pollio. This author of the memoir Goodbye to All That and a noted translation of The Twelve Caesars wrote about a king who refers to himself as \u201cOld King Log\u201d after the execution of his (*)</b> wife Messalina. For ten points, name this author who wrote about the reigns of Tiberius and Caligula in I, Claudius.", "answer": "Robert von Ranke<em><b> Graves</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>In this court case, Thomas Addis Emmet and Thomas J. Oakley represented the defendant who had earlier served as the fifth governor of New Jersey. (+) John Marshall found that the word \u201camong\u201d in Article I, Section 8 of the Constitution was central to the decision of this case, which came about after one state\u2019s Court of Chancery issued an injunction against a company operating out of Elizabethtown. Robert (*) </b> Livingston and Robert Fulton\u2019s monopoly on New York navigation resulted in, for ten points, what case that established the federal government\u2019s sole ability to decide on matters of interstate commerce?", "answer": "<em><b> Gibbons v. Ogden</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In this city in 1775, sailors from the Derby raised a red flag and bombarded town hall during an insurrection against slave-trading merchants cutting their wages. Along with Manchester, this city was the first to be (+) connected by rail to another city. This city was the port of registry for both the Lusitania and the Titanic. This city is the site of the oldest Chinese community in Europe as well as the UK\u2019s oldest Black community, established as a result of this city surpassing Bristol as Europe\u2019s most active (*) </b> slave trading port. For ten points, name this British port in Merseyside from which the Beatles hailed.", "answer": "<em><b> Liverpool</b></em>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}], "bonuses": []}